"The Best Way to Test for Vitamin B12 Deficiency"
Unfortunately, many
diagnoses of B12 deficiency
are still made or dismissed
based solely
on a single measurement
of vitamin B12 levels
in the blood.
Why is that unfortunate?
Well, first of all, there is
remarkable variability
between the results obtained
with different
commercially available
B12 blood tests.
The same sample of blood
can come in at 240 pmol/L
in one lab
and almost double that
in another.
Secondly, there is significant
day-to-day variation
of serum B12
within one individual.
Here, researchers tested people
once a week for 10 weeks,
and the variation
in each individual
could be as much
as 100 points or more.
One way B12 deficiency
can be missed
is when someone takes
a B12 supplement
right before getting tested,
so, based on their blood levels,
it looks like they have
more than enough
even if they’re actually
suffering a serious deficiency.
On the other hand, perhaps
as many as one in five people
who test positive
for B12 deficiency
based on low blood B12 levels
may not actually be deficient.
And then there are those with
symptomatic B12 deficiency
who test fine.
As many as five percent
of patients
who end up being diagnosed
with vitamin B12 deficiency
have blood B12 concentrations
above a commonly used cut-off
of about 150 pmol/L,
and even more have abnormal
MMA or homocysteine levels,
which are signs
of functional B12 deficiency
even if overt symptoms
are not apparent.
Levels of these metabolites
may not normalize
until our blood levels
get up to around 400 pmol/L.
So, maybe the traditional
cut-off is too low.
And it’s not just
lab test abnormalities,
those with marginal B12 levels
score worse
on hand dexterity tests,
suggesting they have covert
diminished nerve function.
Most seriously, we can have
life-threatening B12 deficiency
with normal blood levels.
Here, these two people
were misdiagnosed
as having a bone marrow cancer,
since it couldn’t be B12,
look how high their levels are.
As many as one third of patients
with one of the most dreaded
outcomes of B12 deficiency,
subacute combined degeneration
of the spinal cord,
had normal or even elevated
levels of B12 in their blood.
We’re not sure why,
but sometimes
the test just fails.
Well, that’s not good.
Now, if your test result
is really low,
like under 100 pg/mL,
there’s about
a 90 percent chance
you are truly B12 deficient,
but if the cut-off amount
is higher like 200 pg/mL,
then actual B12 deficiency
could be missed
as much as half the time
if you aren’t showing symptoms.
The reason
it’s so hard to pin down
the rate of false positives
and false negatives
is there’s no gold standard
test to compare it to.
Some studies suggest
measuring the levels
of the biologically active
form of B12,
but a wide variation
in levels is also shown
depending, in part, on which lab
is running the blood test.
Some recommend
using a combination of tests
to improve accuracy.
For example, one or both
of the functional measures
of vitamin B12,
MMA, methylmalonic acid,
and homocysteine,
perhaps especially
when B12 values
are in that so-called
"grey zone"
between 150
and 300 pmol/L or so.
Those functional measures
are pretty sensitive,
meaning if you are B12 deficient
there’s more than
a 95 percent chance
these tests will pick that up.
But there are problems
with so-called specificity,
meaning there are other reasons
values can be abnormal,
like diminished kidney function
in the case of MMA,
and folate deficiency
in the case of homocysteine.
In summary, accurate assessment
of vitamin B12 status
is problematic,
and there is no consensus
as to the best biomarker
or combination
of biomarkers to use.
From a public health standpoint,
what if we just make sure
everyone’s getting their B12?
At least 25 countries
have mandatory
fortification of staples
with vitamin B12,
and that certainly helps.
But in terms of testing,
if you have classic
B12 deficiency symptoms,
even if you have normal
B12 levels in your blood,
and even if your MMA
and homocysteine levels
are normal,
a therapeutic trial
of B12 supplementation
should be considered.
Meaning, why not just try B12
and see
if your symptoms improve?
For example, if you have
neuropathy symptoms,
numbness, pins and needles,
loss of a sense of position,
or experience
a vibration sensation,
maybe you should try going
all out with B12 injections
to be absolutely sure.
Are B12 injections necessary to
correct B12 deficiency, though?
Can it just be treated
with oral B12,
and what’s the best source?
I’ll answer all those questions next.